Guide to the North African Jewish Manuscript Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
North African Jewish manuscript collection
1714-2000
1800-1950
MS 1825
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
27.17
(44 boxes)
The collection includes manuscripts from Morocco, Algeria, Tunisia and Libya. It consists of legal documents concerning such issues as marriage, divorce, property, inheritance, and business dealings of all kinds. In addition, there are manuscripts of poetry, liturgy, mystical texts, folk customs and beliefs, homilies and more. They are in Hebrew, Judeo-Arabic, Judeo-Spanish, Arabic, French, Spanish and Italian and date from the eighteenth to the mid-twentieth century.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Judaica Collection, 2003, 2006, 2013-2015. Bulk of collection purchased by the Judaica Collection from Yeshayahu Vinograd and Moshe Rosenfeld.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in sixteen series and two additions: I. Fe?s, 1755-circa 1960. II. Sefrou, 1754-1940. III. Mekne?s, 1718-circa 2000. IV. Marrakech, 1825-1862. V. Northern/Spanish Morocco, 1720-1957. VI. Tafilalt, 1767-1981. VII. Essaouira, 1844-1957. VIII. Casablanca, circa 1800-1965. IX. Rabat/Salé, 1852-1960. X. Southern Morocco, 1789-1954. XI. Morocco (general), circa 1790-circa 1950. XII. Palestine, Europe, Americas, Egypt, 1714-1962. XIII. Tunisia, 1818-1946. XIV. Libya, 1868-1960. XV. Algeria and Eastern Morocco, 1788-1949. XVI. Marriage contracts (ketubot), 1766-1951.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes manuscripts from Morocco, Algeria, Tunisia and Libya. It consists of legal documents concerning such issues as marriage, divorce, property, inheritance, and business dealings of all kinds. In addition, there are manuscripts of poetry, liturgy, mystical texts, folk customs and beliefs, homilies and more. They are in Hebrew, Judeo-Arabic, Judeo-Spanish, Arabic, French, Spanish and Italian and date from the eighteenth to the mid-twentieth century. The heart of the collection is the material relating to the Jews of Morocco; it was the largest and most influential in the region. Jewish settlement in Morocco has long and illustrious history that goes back to Greco/Roman times. Over the centuries the community produced many noted scholars, rabbis, poets, men of commerce, and statesmen. The Jewish population was composed of groups indigenous to the region and Jews that immigrated to Morocco from Spain and Portugal. While Jewish life has ceased to exist in most Muslim countries, Morocco still has a small Jewish community. The manuscripts come from most regions and cities in the country. These include Casablanca, Fès, Marrakech, Mogador (also known as Essaouira), Meknès, Rabat, Sefrou, Tétouan and Tangier. There is also material from smaller and less well-known towns and villages.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Amulets (Judaism) -- Africa, North; Divorce -- Religious aspects -- Judaism; Folk religion -- Africa, North; Jewish sermons -- Africa, North; Jews -- Africa, North -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Algeria -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Libya -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Morocco -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Tunisia -- History -- Sources; Ketubah -- Africa, North; Manuscripts, Hebrew -- Africa, North; Manuscripts, Judeo-Arabic -- Africa, North; Piyutim; Rabbinical courts -- Africa, North; Responsa; Abi-Ḥasira, Jacob ben Masoud, 1808-1880; Abiṭbol, ʻAmor, 1782-1854; Attar, Judah ben Jacob ibn, 1655-1733; Ben Nayim, Yosef, 1882-1962; Berdugo, Petaḥyah Mordekhai, 1764-1820; Berdugo, Refaʼel, 1747-1821; Berdugo, Yaʻaḳov, -1901; Corcos, Yeshuʻah, 1832-1929; Hakhmon, Yissakhar, 1872-1960; Ibn Danan, Shelomoh, 1848-1929; Ibn Ẓur, Jacob ben Reuben, 1673-1752; Kalfon, Mosheh, ha-Kohen, 1874-1950; Meśaś, Yosef, 1892-1974; Monsonego, Raphael Aharon, approximately 1760-1840; Monsonégo, Yédidia, -1867; Monsonego, Yehochoua, 1826-1892; Sarfaty, Abner Israel, 1827-1884; Serero, Matityah; Sḳali, Daṿid, ha-Kohen, 1861-; Ṭoledano, Yaʻaḳov, -1771
- Fe?s, 1755-circa 1960; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I is comprised of documents from Fès (Fez, F?s), a community in north-central Morocco that was at one time a major center of Jewish life in Morocco. The documents include rabbinic decisions and other legal documents, bills of sale, and correspondence, mainly from the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.
  The first section (Box 1) contains documents signed by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli (and one signed by Shelomoh ha-Levi ibn Yuli). Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli (1841-1926) was the secretary of the rabbinic court of Fe?s. This position made him a frequent signatory to decisions of the court, although neither he nor his family was originally from Fe?s. Ibn Yuli's outsider status prevented him from advancing to a position as a judge on the court, but also contributed to his reputation as a fair and impartial adjudicator.
  The documents in Box 2 relate to the Serarah (governing or venerated) families, a group of families who dominated the religious leadership of the community of Fe?s. These families included ibn Tsur, ibn Danan, Monsonego, Sarfati, Serero and ben Attar. From the fifteenth century through the mid- twentieth century, the power and influence of these families passed from generation to generation. They were the families that had the right to take on the various positions of the religious leadership of the community. These included judgeships of the rabbinic court, appointments of ritual slaughterers, and membership in the burial society (H?evra Kadisha).
  Boxes 3 and 4 contain other documents from Fe?s, as well as those without the place explicitly stated, but with handwriting, subject matter, or names suggesting that the document was originally from Fe?s or from either Fe?s or Mekne?s. Oversize documents from Fe?s are in Box 32.
  - Ibn Yuli
    - Collection of rabbinic decisions, 1898; MS.1825.0012; 1 v. ([3], 140 leaves); 20 centimeters; original leather binding with partially worn-off leather clasps. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Place: Fe?s. 140 numbered pages of legal documents signed by rabbis of Fe?s and scribes of the court, including Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli, Shelomoh Sasson, Refael Mosheh Maimaran, and David Eliyahu Harosh. Most of the decisions are from the year 1898. At the end of the volume and on the backs of several of the pages are additions written in pencil, partly in Judeo-Arabic. The three pages in the front of the volume contain a table of contents beginning with the second document. Bound volume, similar to MS.1825.0011.
    - Collection of rabbinic decisions, 1898; MS.1825.0013; 1 v. (164 leaves); 19 centimeters; original tooled leather binding. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Place: Fe?s. Collection of over 100 rabbinic decisions, mostly from the year 1900, mainly concerning matters of interpersonal relations, signed by the rabbis Refa?el Ya?ak?ov ben Attar, Yehonatan Amozeg, Hayim David Serero, Mosheh Hamu, Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli, and others.
    - Rabbinic decisions, 1910; MS.1825.0024; 30 pages; 23 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Place: Fès. A copy of rabbinic decisions signed by a rabbinic authority in the city of Fès in the beginning of the twentieth century. One of the famous rabbis who signed here is Shelomoh ibn Danan and others are Shelomoh ha-Levi ibn Yuli and Shelomoh Sasson.
    - Legal documents concerning care of orphans, 1851, 1856; MS.1825.0030; 12 pages (8 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Place: Fès. A copy of legal documents concerning a guardian of orphans who sold property on their behalf. Signed by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli and Shelomoh Sasson.
    - Four documents concerning inheritance and rights of minors, 1895, 1902 or 1903; MS.1825.0098; 4 pages (2 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Place: Fès. The first document is written and signed by Shelomoh Sasson and Mosheh Moyal, 1895 (the date in the document has a mistake). It concerns a small apartment belonging to Saida bat Aharon Shoshan in the neighborhood of Nwawel close to the new cemetery. After her death the apartment became the property of her sons Eliyahu and Hayim. Afterwards her son Hayim died leaving two small boys and their uncle, Eliyahu, became the custodian for his brother's sons. Later Eliyahu's wife Miryam tried to claim the portion of the small boys. The rabbis defend the rights of these two boys in their decision. The second document signed by the same two rabbis deals with a detail of the former document. The third document from the year Heshvan 1895 deals with the same people and the same subject with some new information. The fourth document deals with the same subject, but now concerning Miryam the wife of Eliyahu. This one is signed by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli and Shelomoh Sasson in Tevet 1902 or 1903. There is a fifth text dealing with the same subject, but we have only its first part (any additional pages are missing).
    - Two manuscripts concerning a loan of money, 1899; MS.1825.0100; 4 pages (3 blank); 18 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Place: Fès. The first one concerns a loan of money given by three people to Avraham Harosh ben Yehudah. It is signed by Shelomoh Sasson and Matityah Serero. There is additional testimony concerning the same problem signed in the same year by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli and Shelomoh Sasson.
    - Document regarding a dispute between neighbors over privacy matters, 1899; MS.1825.0225; 4 pages (3 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Place: Fès. The neighbors had windows facing each other in close proximity. This was a common problem in the Jewish quarter (mellah) since houses were very close together. The document is signed by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli and Shelomoh Sasson.
    - Document accompanied by three addenda, 1901; MS.1825.0512; 2 pages; 30 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Place: Fès. One of the signatories is Yosef ibn Yuli.
    - Copy of a document concerning real estate in Fès, 1803, circa 1880-circa 1920; MS.1825.0555; 4 pages; 34 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 2)
      Place: Fès. The original document was written in 1803 in Gibraltar and was copied in Fès approximately one hundred years later. This copy is signed by Mosheh Attia and Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli.
    - Document relating to inheritance of the heirs of Menasheh ha-Kohen, 1886; MS.1825.0558; 4 pages (1 blank); 36 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 2)
      Place: Fès. The document is signed by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli and Eliyahu Attia, verified by Refael ibn Tsur and Yosef Serero.
    - Annulment of a first ketubah and the writing of a new one, 1911; MS.1825.0576; 4 pages (2 blank); 36 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 2)
      Place: Fès. The husband is Binyamin ben Simhon (the document mentions six generations of his family) and his wife is Ester bat Makhluf ben Shimon. Signed by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli and Mosheh [?]
    - Copy of a bill of sale, 1866; MS.1825.0653; 2 pages; 36 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Place: Fès. Dated Heshvan 5627. Signed by Yehudah Asulin and Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli.
    - Legal document, 1890; MS.1825.0658; 4 pages (3 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Place: Fès.
    - Legal document concerning a courtyard, 1886; MS.1825.0660; 4 pages ( 2 blank); 18 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Legal document, 1901; MS.1825.0662; 4 pages (2 blank); 18 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Place: Fès. The document is dated Kislev 5662 (December 1901).
    - Legal document, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0677; 4 pages (3 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Legal document, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0679; 4 pages (3 blank); 19 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Legal document, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0686; 4 pages (3 blank); 15 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Document with regard to the sale of a house, 1905; MS.1825.0783; 4 pages (3 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Place: Fès. Parties to the sale are Yitshak and Masud ben Shelush and Makhluf Dahan. The document is signed by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli and Yaakov Berdugo.
    - Document from Fès, 1875; MS.1825.0847; 2 pages; 29 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli, Yehochoua Monsonego and others.
    - Document concerning the division of a business among partners, 1877; MS.1825.0860; 4 pages (3 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Place: Fès. The partners were Menasheh ha-Kohen and Makhluf Aflalo, as well as the heirs of Mordekhai Aflalo.The document is signed by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli and Hayim David ha-Kohen.
    - Written permission of a woman to immigrate with her husband to the land of Israel, 1890; MS.1825.0890; 4 pages (3 blank); 22 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Eliyahu Attia and Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli.
    - Document written by a woman in Fès, 1865; MS.1825.0893; 4 pages (3 blank); 28 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Mosheh Attia and Shemuel ibn Tsur. An addition is signed by Mosheh Attia and Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli.
    - Document relating to a house in Fès, 1886; MS.1825.0902; 4 pages (2 blank); 18 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Yosef ibn Yuli and Eliyahu Attia.
    - Document of Shelomoh Monsonego concerning a real estate transaction, 1877; MS.1825.0904; 1 leaf; 30 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Place: Fès. Shelomoh Monsonego commits himself not to sell real estate without the permission of Maimon Ben Shoshan. Signed by Mosheh Attia and Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli.
    - Document with regard to real estate, 1886; MS.1825.0905; 4 pages (1 blank); 15 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Two documents, one concerning a small house and the other concerning inheritance in the Monsonego family, Circa 1880-circa 1920; MS.1825.0910.1; 2 pages; 23 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Place: Fès. The first document is one and a half pages, and only the beginning of the second document is present. The first document is not from Fès. It is a copy of a document concerning a small house. The original document is from 1865 and was signed by Yisrael ha-Sarfati. In addition there are also signatures of Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli and Shelomoh Sasson. The second document regards Yehudah Monsonego, the son of Yédidia, and his heirs: two sons, three daughters and his wife. The rest of the document is missing.
    - Document of disinheritance, 1896; MS.1825.0910.2; 2 pages; 23 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Place: Fès. The second page is a document concerning the appointment of a guardian. On both documents are the signatures of Yosef ha-Levi Ibn Yuli and Shelomoh Sasson.
    - Bill of sale of a house to Shaul Ben Shoshan ben Maimon, 1900; MS.1825.0910.3; 4 pages (2 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli and Shemtov ibn Attar.
    - Document affirming the payment of debts, 1902; MS.1825.0910.4; 4 pages (1 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Place: Fès. The document is signed by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli and Shelomoh Sasson.
    - Three documents relating to the purchase of a house by Tamar, the daughter of Abba Serero, 1902, 1904; MS.1825.0910.5; 4 pages (2 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Place: Fès. Among the signatories are Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli and Shelomoh Sasson.
    - Document of a bill of sale, 1902; MS.1825.0918; 1 leaf; 23 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli, Shelomoh Sasson, and others.
    - Group of seven documents, 1886; MS.1825.0924; 2 pages; 36 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 4)
      Place: Fès. The subjects of the documents are ownership rights, clarification of documents, sale of property. Signed by Eliyahu Attia and Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli.
    - The conclusion of one document followed by a second document concerning ownership rights, 1905; MS.1825.0925; 4 pages (2 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 4)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli and Refael Yaakov Attar. The second document relates to ownership rights. The owner of this document is Makhluf from the village of [Alboalil?]. The second document also has the signature of Shaul Shoshan.
    - Document concerning real estate, 1881; MS.1825.0970; 4 pages (3 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Place: Fès. Among the signatories is Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli.
    - Detailed document regarding a compromise between neighbors concerning an extension to a building, 1880; MS.1825.0972; 4 pages (3 blank) ;37 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Place: Fès. The document is signed by Yosef ha-Levi Ibn Yuli, Eliyahu Attia, Hayim David ha-Kohen, and others.
    - Document in Judeo-Arabic regarding a sale of a house, 1909; MS.1825.0982; 4 pages (3 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Place: Fès. The document is signed by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli and another person.
    - Document regarding a business transaction, 1906; MS.1825.0983; 4 pages (3 blank); 36 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Place: Fès. The document is signed by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli and Refael Yaakov Attar.
    - Document regarding a place in the Nawawil neighborhood in the Jewish district of Fès, 1898; MS.1825.0996; 4 pages (3 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Place: Fès. The document is signed by Yosef ha-Levi ibn Yuli. The page on the right of the document is written in classical Arabic.
  - Serarah families
    - Rabbinic manuscripts, 1800s; MS.1825.0010; Approximately 90 pages; 21 centimeters. Pages sewn together, no cover. (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Place: Fès. A group of manuscripts bound together and copied in Fès, most probably in the nineteenth century. The texts were composed, however, in the beginning of the eighteenth century. They include decisions made by Judah ben Jacob ibn Attar, Jacob ben Reuben ibn Ẓur, Yehudah ʻUziʼel, Saʻadia ʻAḳiva ibn Danan, Shaul ibn Danan, and others. Most of these rabbis were the religious leaders of the city of Fès at the end of the seventeenth and the first half of the eighteenth century. The scribe is Yitsḥak Kohen. Many of the texts are queries with detailed answers to various Jewish legal questions (responsa). In addition, one finds in this collection a homily on the subject of establishing fixed times for prayers.
    - Rabbinic decisions concerning inheritance, property rights and other issues, 1800s; MS.1825.0021; 52 pages (38 blank); 22 centimeters. (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Place: Fès. A collection of rabbinic decisions bound together copied in the nineteenth century, mainly from the community of Fès, signed by Hayim David Serero, Yonatan Serero, Raphael Aharon Monsonego, Yaakov Serero, Yaakov Berdugo, Shaul Yeshuah Abitbol, Yédidia Monsonégo and other sages. One decision from Rabat concerning divorce is signed by rabbis from the d'Avila family. Two responsa signed by Judah ben Jacob ibn Attar (1655-1733) and others originally date to the seventeenth or eighteenth century. Topics include women's inheritance rights, legal issues concerning rights of ownership (ḥazaḳah), and cases between Jews and Muslims.
    - Legal text written by student learning to make halakhic decisions, Circa 1830-circa 1850; MS.1825.0028; 38 pages; 32 centimeters. Corners and edges are crumbling, some loss of text. (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Place: Fès. Text written by a student, Yehochoua Monsonego, who is learning to make halakhic decisions under the supervision of his father, Yédidia Monsonégo. (Yehochoua was born in 1826 and died in 1892. See Mosheh Amar, Nishmat Hayyim, pages 16-17). The document contains mostly notes concerning halakhic decision making as well as some drafts of halakhic decisions.
    - Collection of ten documents related to Refael ibn Tsur ha-aḥaron, Circa 1880-circa 1920; MS.1825.0034.01-.10; 10 documents, each 1-4 pages; 16 centimeters. (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Place: Fès. A collection of ten documents related directly to Refael ibn Tsur ha-aḥaron from the end of the nineteenth century through 1917. Several are laudatory letters to him on different subjects. One of them is even a poem expounding on the fine qualities of Refael. Another document, written by Refael himself, lists seven generations of his family going back to Reuven ibn Tsur, the father of Jacob ben Reuben ibn Ẓur.
    - Document concerning the sale of real estate by a woman and an appeal by her brother-in-law, 1896; MS.1825.0070; 1 leaf; 37 centimeters. (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Place: Fès. The document concerns a sale of real estate by Simha bat Shelomoh ben Sabbah, the wife of David ben Avraham Kadosh. She sold the real estate to Yehudah ben Asaraf. The document is signed by Refael ben Yaakov Attar. There are two additions to this document; the most important is the longer one which records an appeal by Mosheh ben Kadosh, the brother of her husband, who claimed part of the proceeds. The document does not include the decision regarding the appeal.
    - Document concerning a bequest by a woman to local religious institutions, 1855; MS.1825.0079; 4 pages (2 blank); 36 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 1)
      Place: Fès. Document concerning donations by a woman named Kamra, probably the daughter of the great rabbi Shemuel Mansano, from the year 1855. She decided to make a tremendous and important donation including Torah Scrolls to the Hekdesh, the local religious institutions, namely synagogues, the burial society, and so on. In this document she declares that while she is healthy she wants everyone to know that if she becomes sick and dies, all of her possessions should be given to the Hekdesh. She designates the great rabbis Yédidia Monsonégo and Matityah Serero to be responsible for carrying out her decision. The document was signed by Shelomoh ha-Kohen Skali and Shelomoh ha-Levi and confirmed by the rabbis Yaakov ben Simḥon and Refael ibn Tsur.
    - Collection of different texts including a few letters written to rabbis in the city of Fès and three liturgical poems (piyyutim), Circa 1880-circa 1920; MS.1825.0084; 8 pages; 22 centimeters. Pamphlet. Blue paper. (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Place: Fès. Collection of different texts including a few letters written to rabbis in the city of Fès. One letter is written to Refael Ibn Tsur. In the letter the writer indicates a long series of his ancestors, at least ten generations, going back to Jacob ben Reuben ibn Ẓur and his father and grandfather in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries. Another letter is written to Shelomoh ibn Danan, one of the great rabbis in the first third of the twentieth century. This letter also indicates a series of the writer's ancestors to the fifteenth century. Two other texts are liturgical poems (piyyutim) written by David ibn Attar, also of Fès. A third poem is written by Saadia ben Yaakov ibn Danan.
    - Legal documents concerning repayment of a debt and related issues, Before 1750-1804; MS.1825.0133; 2 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 2, Folder 7)